After a few million interactions, magic
happens, which is that you go from noise
to programs. You start to see uh complex
programs appear on these tables. This is
the most exciting plot that I've made in
the last few years, and it's the one
that's on the cover of the book. You can
see that in the beginning, it's not very
computational. And then a sudden
transition takes place here. It looks
like a phase transition.
This is the book that I hear is making
the rounds at Sakana, which I'm very
happy to hear. The big one on the right,
what is intelligence is sort of the Lord
of the Rings. And what is life on the
left is kind of the Hobbit. So it's kind
of the single and it's also chapter one
of of what is intelligence. So it goes
kind of inside the other one. Mostly
what I'll be talking about today is is
what's in these two books, but with um
with quite a bit more detail, more
mathematical detail since I think this
is a really good audience for that. And
I'll also be connecting it uh a bit with
some of the the bigger themes of the A
life conference and community and dare I
dare I say even movement. You know in
particular I actually wanted to begin
with this wonderful sort of open
problems in artificial life uh summary
paper which you know has a number of of
very illustrious co-authors uh you know
at least one of whom we heard from
yesterday and and more than one of whom
are are here at the conference. This is
uh you know open problems uh 14 open
problems in artificial life in the year
2000. How does life arise from the
non-living? Uh how do the transition uh
to life uh in an artificial chemistry or
in silicon environment can occur and why
it occurs? I'm sure many of you know
this was the the problem that bedeled
Darwin. You know he made one of the most
uh rich and and uh explanatorily
powerful theories in you know ever in
science in in discovering how evolution
works. But he was unable to explain how
evolution got started. Uh he at some
point in one of his letters said, you
know, you might as well talk about the
origin of matter. Um I think that the
origin of matter and the origin of life
might actually be one and the same thing
and evolution might actually be the
answer to that question, but it's an
evolution that includes uh a term that
Darwin did not account for in his
original formulation. In section B of
these questions, uh determine what is
inevitable in the open-ended evolution
of life. uh I'm I'm hoping to speak a
little bit about that too. Create a
formal framework for synthesizing
dynamical hierarchies at all scales and
develop a theory of information
processing, information flow and
information generation for evolving
systems. Um I won't be going into the
information theory in any detail. Um but
uh but hopefully we'll we'll set up the
problem in in a perhaps somewhat new way
that that I I hope will help to do that.
Um and finally in section C, how is life
related to mind, machines and culture?
Um if I have time, I will get into this
as well and talk a bit about the
emergence of intelligence and mind in an
artificial living system and uh the
influence of machines on the next major
evolutionary transition of life. So uh
you know it was really cool to to read
this paper from 2020 and to see how much
of the perspective uh that that um uh
that you had already been exploring then
uh you know feels you know right and
consistent with uh you know with with a
sort of fresh look at this at these
problems in 2025. Let me just begin with
uh with this question of souls. It used
to be in the 19th century and and
earlier uh that we thought that uh life
had some vital force or spirit that
animated it and made it different from
inanimate matter. In the 19th century
when we began to figure out organic
chemistry and be able to synthesize ura
and so on u the the idea that that no we
should really adopt a strictly
materialist perspective because there's
nothing special or different about the
matter in us versus the matter anywhere
else in the universe uh took hold. And
that's progress for sure. But um but it
also you know when we when we embrace
atoms and materialism fully we're left
with some uh some questions about you
know what differentiates life from
non-life then you know like what can we
even say about life there are at least
some biologists who who say well maybe
it's not even meaningful to talk about
any difference between life and non-life
but I I don't think that that's true uh
and I think that the answer to the to
the conundrum is to invoke function
function is the thing that life has that
non-life doesn't have. In other words,
if we, you know, just to give you a
little parable, if I were to come back
from the future with this object and you
ask me what it is, uh, and I tell you it
is an artificial kidney with a
100red-year lifespan, you can implant it
in a body and it'll it'll, you know,
it'll work the way your kidneys do.
It'll it'll filter ura from the blood
and so on. Um, that's a really important
piece of information, but it's not a
material or a materialist piece of
information. It's not something that you
could read off from the atoms. uh and
you know those atoms could be I don't
know tungsten filaments or carbon nano
tubes are made out of some technology we
don't understand now or it could be
organic it could be made out of uh
cloned tissue um and and the point is
that it working as a kidney doesn't
depend on that matter there is a kind of
separation of concerns between the
matter and the function and so there's
some real sense in which the function is
like a spirit or like something like
something immaterial it's not material
and yet it also relies of course on the
physics of what's going on you can't
have the spirit without the matter as it
were. So function is really important
and uh and function is something that uh
uh you know a rock on a non-living
planet uh somewhere doesn't have. You
know if you if you break a rock on a
non-living planet you now have two
rocks. You don't have a broken rock. Uh
if you break a kidney you now no longer
have a working kidney. That's the
difference between something functional
and something non-functional. This idea
of function was formalized by Alan
Turing who never intended the touring
machine to actually be built uh when he
wrote it in 1936. But there is one that
was built by Mike Davyy in 2010. I don't
need to review Touring machines with all
of you of course um uh you you all know
how they how they work. But I do want to
review briefly uh Vonoman's update to
Turring's thinking about computation uh
which which he did a few years later.
This was published postumously after
Vonoman died. Um but the idea behind
behind vonoman's thinking is he was
trying to answer the same question that
Schroinger had quite had asked in his
what is life book. Uh and in particular
he was trying to ask the question if you
have a robot that is swimming around uh
on a uh you know in in a pond and the
pond has lots of loose Legos around.
There were no I don't know if there were
Legos in 1950 but let's pretend there
were Legos in 1950. And the job of the
robot is to assemble those Legos into a
new robot like itself. you know, there's
something a little bit mysterious about
that. It feels a little bit like pulling
yourself up by your own bootstraps or
like a paradox. And so he asked, what
does it take for something to be able to
make something like itself? Uh, which
seems uh hard, almost paradoxical. And
his conclusion was, well, you need to
have instructions for how to make a MI.
You need to have a tape with
instructions for how to make a MI, and
you need to have a universal constructor
that will follow the uh the instructions
on that on that tape in order to
assemble the necessary parts. And you
also need to have a tape copier uh so
that you can give your offspring uh a
copy of that tape. And by the way, the
tape has to also include the
instructions for making the universal
constructor and the tape copier. And if
those things all hold, then you have
life. You have something that can build
itself. Uh and uh what's what's so
profound about about Vonoyman's insight?
I mean, first of all, he predicted all
of this before we knew the structure and
function of DNA, before we understood
what ribosomes were or had discovered
DNA polymerase. So he called it exactly
right. Those all of those things really
do exist uh inside cells and he figured
this out from pure theory never having
set foot in a bolab. The the profound
insight is that he said by the way a
universal constructor is a universal
touring machine. Those are literally one
and the same thing. And by by making
that observation what he discovered was
that life is literally embodied
computation. It is computational. You
cannot have life without having
computation. So obviously not everything
that is alive reproduces but everything
that is alive has to be able to make
itself. It has to be able to do some
combination of healing, growing,
maintaining itself, reproducing. All of
that is autopoesis. All of that involves
self- construction and all of that
necessarily involves a universal
constructor. Now what do I mean by
embodied computation? This is a really
important distinction between vonoyman
and touring. in touring the symbols that
the that the head writes are different
from the head itself and the tape and uh
and the table of rules that the that the
head follows whereas in vonoyman it's
it's more like a 3D printer uh the the
memory is atoms not abstract symbols in
other words uh you know you could think
about a touring machine as like this
laptop uh you know which can't extrude
another laptop out the side but a
vonoyman replicator is like a
combination of a laptop and a 3D printer
that can print another laptop. So its
memory is actually atoms. Uh that's what
I mean by embodied. So I don't mean
embodied in the ways that a lot of
roboticists talk about embodied. I mean
that that there is a closure between the
uh the medium in which the computation
happens and the thing that is actually
doing the computation. That's the key.
So uh computation that is embodied in
that sense and that is autopetic is
alive. You can't reproduce non-trivally
evolvably without without uh
computation. No computation, no life. Uh
I do want to say a word briefly about
what I mean by computation. Uh and in
this I'm following the the work of uh
Susan Stephanie, Dominick Horesman, uh
Rob Wagner, Viv Kendon. Uh this is from
a nice paper they wrote in 2023 relating
uh the evolution of a physical system
and the computation that it does. So you
know on top you have logical gates, on
the bottom you have uh you know
transistors in in your computer. Uh this
is important because you know there's
there are no bits in a computer. There
are just voltages that go up and down.
In fact, you know, even the voltages are
an abstraction of something further, you
know, if we go further down. But you
know the the point is that you have to
coarse grain those voltages into bits
and then you have to have a logical
machine that talks about how those bits
uh evolve. What are the what are the
what are the computational processes
that those bits undergo and there is a
mapping from the physical system to the
logical system and vice versa. uh when
we say something computes what we mean
is that it is possible to construct such
a mapping and that therefore as the
physical system evolves that is
equivalent to the logical system
evolving. Uh so you know there are some
caveats you can have stochcastic
computation in which there's a little
bit of randomness injected so it doesn't
have to be fully deterministic. Uh
another really important caveat is that
you don't want that description to be
infinitely complex. Otherwise, you could
have the trivial case of saying like,
you know, the water in the sen is a
computer and the longer my computation,
I just need to make my description
longer and longer in order to match. No,
that doesn't work either. You need a a
kind of alchems razor uh description
that uh for it to be valid. But this is
a good definition of computation, but it
emphasizes that there is something
subjective about computation. You need
to have a model for how the uh how the
physical system translates into the
logical system in order for any of this
stuff to work. There are implications
about entropy, free energy and heat and
so on in this model. Uh and in
particular uh you as you all know we've
talked already you know ectctor Zenil in
his very elegant uh talk of a couple of
days ago talked about uh and actually
Chris Kempus also talked about the
landour limit uh and the fact that in a
computational system you're constantly
reducing the entropy of of your state
space and in doing so you therefore
require free energy. So uh you know you
need need to have free energy available
and you need to eject waste heat. The
exception in a way only proves the rule
which is reversible computation. In
reversible computation you generate
ancill uh and that's equivalent to just
saying there's no exhaust but you know
then you either have to keep on making
your computer bigger and bigger and
bigger as you accumulate these ancill
you have to uh shrink what you consider
to be the computer and then you're back
to reversible to to non-reversible
computation once again. three important
fallacies that I want to point out
before continuing. One of them I will
call the Seapolski error. Robert
Seapolski you know has written famously
about uh people not having free will uh
because we're built on physical systems.
Uh you know the physics is is uh you
know if you like deterministic let's set
aside quantum mechanics uh and stuff
like this. Let's let's imagine we live
in a Newtonian universe. It's fine. It's
good enough. The point is that physics
is reversible. uh all of the basic
physics that we understand uh whether
that's you know Newton's equations
Maxwell's equations Einstein's equations
quantum mechanics all of those are
essentially time reversible uh so you
can move them either forward or back
computation is not reversible when I add
you know 3 + 5 to get 8 once I've got
the 8 uh and I've you know I haven't
kept my ancillates around let's say I no
longer know what was added in order to
make the eight computation is inherently
irreversible and so to say that what
true of the physical system is also true
of the of the computational system or
the logical system is is not is not the
case and reversibility would be one
trivial example of how that is not the
case. Causation by the way only makes
sense in the light of irreversibility.
All right. So if you have a purely
physical system then you know to say
that A causes B is equivalent to saying
that B causes A because you know
everything is kind of a block universe
if you like in a uh you know in in that
kind of setup. But in computation uh you
know you you can you can talk about
causality because there are ifs and
thens in there. And this once again
connects with the way uh you know the
way ectctor was talking about how you
know essentially nothing in nothing in
causation makes sense except in the
light of computation. Uh which I fully
agree with. Uh another fallacy uh we
could call the the early victinstein
error. If we say something like birds
exist in the world uh line one of the
tractatus logical philosophy didn't say
birds but whatever. You can't say birds
exist or birds don't exist in a way that
is independent of a model of the
universe. Uh there are no birds in
physics. There are no birds in this
underlying dynamical system. When we
start talking about birds, we already
are talking about having some kind of
some kind of model. And once we start
talking about models, uh you've got
causality, reversibility, all kinds of
other irreversibility, all kinds of
other things in play. And none of these
statements are are are airtight. Uh they
all rely on on an observer. Uh this is
kind of Kant as well I guess. Uh and
this leads to the the early linenets
error uh or the same error that the good
old F good old fashioned AI
practitioners had which is that that
intelligence could be carried out by by
just having a series of uh programs of
of sort of strictly logical uh you know
deductions or inductions. That doesn't
work. This is why good old fashioned AI
never never panned out. And and the
reason is that that you can't start out
with like in math with propositions that
are self-sufficient. Even math is not
self-sufficient, but let's pretend for a
moment and just move from there and kind
of do an algebra in order to work
various things out. When when your
propositions are not airtight and when
you're looking only at regularities and
patterns, this good oldfashioned uh AI
idea simply cannot work. And that's
that's why we never got it to work.
Let's move now to to some of the
artificial life experiments that uh that
uh that I began playing with in at the
end of 2023 and my team and I published
in June of 2024. So just about a year
ago. I think some of you uh many of you
perhaps have heard of these. They're in
the what is life books and I've talked
about them a few times. The the basic
setup here is to try and get
self-replication to get you know
abiogenesis the emergence of life from
non-life to happen in a purely
artificial life system. Uh okay so the
setup is to begin with a minimal touring
complete language uh I used brain [ __ ]
uh because I I really liked the idea of
being able to talk at a conference and
say brain [ __ ] over and over and I'm
fundamentally 12 years old on the
inside. Um but but also because it's
it's uh it it very closely models uh the
touring machine. Uh you know it's it's a
it's a a minimal programming language
only only eight instructions that uh
that looks very touring machineike and
moves the head back and forth. I should
say that in its original version brain
[ __ ] is not embodied computation. It has
basically a separate data tape and code
tape and that means that it cannot make
a copy of itself. So I I made a couple
of modifications to brain [ __ ] that
actually reduce it from eight
instructions to seven in order to make
it embodied. Meaning that as it works on
the tape, it is able to read its own
code and write and write its own code on
that tape as well. There's no separate
console. There's no separation between
the data tape and the uh and the
instruction tape. For those of you who
are unfamiliar with BrainFuck, there is
hello world in it. I'm sure you've
already figured out how it works by just
looking at the program. Um I actually
still haven't, I have to admit. By the
way, this is actually the French brain
[ __ ] page because I thought it was
better uh but translated into English.
It's funnier to read it that way. These
are these are the eight instructions.
You know, the first four are move the
head one step to the left, one step to
the right, increment the bite at the
head, decrement the bite at the head.
We're already halfway through. There's
an input and output instruction, which
in this case really just copy from uh
from one head to another. And there are
jump instructions, open open bracket and
close bracket in order to be able to be
able to make loops. Uh and that's it.
That's all that's all brain [ __ ] is. So
how does how does the uh AIFE experiment
work? The AIFE experiment is called BFF.
Uh the first BF stand for brain [ __ ] and
the second F uh you can draw your own
conclusions. Um but uh you start off
with with a soup of of uh uh I I
actually generally use just 1,000 1,024
tapes. Uh that's enough for this
experiment. Uh so the tapes are of fixed
length. They're of length 64 and they
begin random. So just random bytes. Now,
if a tape is random bytes, that means
that only one in 32 of them or so are
even valid instructions. Most of them
are nos. A no-up will just be skipped
over uh like in most uh programming
languages. So, um so this is what those
tapes look like in the beginning. And
you can see that, you know, the uh I'm
not printing the noops, right? So,
that's all the blank space. Uh the the
operations are quite sparse. On any
given tape, you only have an average of
two instructions or so. And then the
procedure is to pluck two of these tapes
out of the soup at random, concatenate
them end to end, so you have 128 bytes,
and then run uh and then after running,
pull them back apart and put them back
in the soup and repeat. That's it. So
it's just that over and over. That's the
entire experiment. Uh so I'll show you
what happens uh on my laptop
after a few million interactions. um
magic happens which is that you go from
noise to to programs. You start to see
uh complex programs appear on these
tapes. And this is quite wonderful
because these programs take uh you know
they take real effort to reverse
engineer when you when you study them.
You know you it's like studying that
hello world program. You have to you
know they're they're functional in the
sense they really do something. Uh and
it's not trivial to figure out how they
work in order to do that. Uh okay what
are they doing? Well, they're definitely
copying themselves or each other
somehow. We know that because uh if you
know this is a histogram and you could
see, you know, in this case there were
8,000 tapes, there are 5,000 of the top
one, 297 of the next one and so on. So
there's clearly copying going on and
there's this ecology of programs all
copying each other. Uh which is which is
just wonderful to see. I mean that's
that's that's that you know emergence of
of of life in this very functional
minimal sense from randomness. A part of
this is very easy to understand. You
know why why do these things emerge?
Well, because something that copies
itself will be around forever and
something that doesn't copy itself will
be copied over by something that can
copy itself. So, inherently uh something
that can copy itself is more stable than
something that cannot copy itself. So,
it's really just the second law of
thermodynamics but uh but doing
something unexpected which is creating
something more complex because it's more
stable rather than something less
complex which is less stable. This idea
that stability doesn't necessarily mean
uh mean low complexity was worked out in
some detail by Adi Pros the organic
chemist in another book called what is
life. Uh he calls it dynamic kinetic
stability. Meaning usually we think of
stability only in terms of fixed points
in a phase space. But a cycle can be
even more stable than a fixed point. Uh
of course for these cycles to work you
need an input of free energy. Uh but you
know for reasons that we've already gone
into. Uh okay. So mystery mostly solved
but actually mystery not fully solved uh
for for reasons that I will that I will
uh show in a second. But but just to
give you a sense of what of what this
transition looks like from non-life to
life. It's very dramatic. In the
beginning uh you know these interactions
uh only involve you know there only a
few instructions in the soup. It's a
touring gas as Walter Fontano would have
called it. When you do the join and you
run only two operations run in any given
interaction on average uh as as you'd
expect. And that's what it looks like by
the end in this particular run. Uh and
1,374 operations on average are running
per interaction. So the soup has become
intensely computational. Uh there's been
a transition here. And there's a lot
more code uh than than one in 32 uh
bytes. As you can see, this is what that
looks like visually. This is the most
exciting plot that I've made in the last
few years. And it's the one that's on
the cover of the book. So what I've
drawn here are 10 million dots. It's a
scatter plot of interactions. The x-axis
is time and the y-axis for every dot is
how many computations took place. How
many operations took place on that
interaction and you can see that in the
beginning it's not very computational.
And then a sudden transition takes place
here at at 6 million interactions and it
becomes intensely computational. It
looks like a phase transition. In fact,
it is a phase transition. You can also
see that in the the entropy of the soup.
So here I'm just ent I'm just estimating
the entropy of the soup by zipping it
and looking at at the size of the zip
relative to the uh to the whole thing.
You can use any compression algorithm
you like. In the beginning it's
uncompressible. So it's a gas you know
in that touring gas sense because all
the bites are random. And you can see
that there's a dramatic change and
suddenly it becomes extremely
compressible right at that transition
moment. And of course this becomes
compressible because there everything is
copying uh right itself and each other.
So if things are copying themselves then
they'll we know that they'll become very
compressible. But it's cool because if
we think about what the phase of matter
is on the left, it is just like a gas.
Nothing is correlated. What would we
call the phase of matter on the right?
It's not a liquid. It's not a solid.
Right? It has structure. It has
structure at every scale. I think you
have to call that phase of matter life.
Uh that's it's a functional phase of
matter. Uh it means that uh that it that
its parts are different from its other
parts. And if you zoom in or out, you
see more structure. So it's what David
Walpert would call self dissimilar. It's
not a fractal. It's a more like a
multiffractal. I'll explain why in a
moment. Uh okay. Uh how long does it
take this transition to happen? Well um
the the answer is it looks more or less
like an airline distribution or uh a
little bit more precisely like this uh
distribution I call a lockpick
distribution which imagines that there
are steps that have to be undertaken and
those steps have a longtail distribution
of difficulty. And how many steps does
it take? Well, the answer is 12. It
takes 12 steps just like uh getting
sober. I suppose this is a you know a
fit of the empirical to the you know to
the heirlong and the lockpick
distribution is a little hard to see but
the lockpick is a bit better than
heirlong. Heirlong assumes pson lockpick
assumes longtailed but it's a process
phase distribution and and what this
tells you is that there are stepping
stones here. You know you can't get that
transition to life immediately. So
something interesting must be going on
here on the left other than just
randomness. It takes multiple things
happening in order to get to that point.
You know in this case you know it
happens somewhere between 1 million and
uh let's say 7 million uh interactions.
Okay. So um this all suggests that
pretty much any universe by the way that
has a source of randomness uh and can
support computation uh will evolve life
uh you know for this simple dynamical
stability reason. But the big mystery is
why does why does it appear to get more
complex over time? Uh you might have
seen in my little video that you know we
saw some programs emerge and then we saw
the we saw them sort of densify more
instructions appeared and and even more
fundamentally why does this work even
without mutation? I didn't mention but
you know in the original version of BFF
I added some random mutation because you
know we're all taught in school that the
way the way evolution works is chance
and necessity. you know, you mutate
things. You're sort of throwing
spaghetti at the wall and whatever
sticks is what is what does better. And
so you need a source of spaghetti. But
if you do this entire experiment with
the mutation rate cranked all the way
down to zero, you still get the same
exact phenomenon. And that is very
mysterious because if you crank mutation
down to zero, you should have no source
of novelty. You should have no
evolution. Why do you still get this
apparent complexification even with zero
mutation? Uh so let's let's go into some
of the some of the theory of this. By
the end uh we have a replicating entity.
It can engage in standard sort of
population evolution dynamics. This is
the kind of of differential equation
that that one generally writes for this
sort of thing. It's a very general
unsat. Uh this is for you know uh
species uh I let's say they're n
species. They could be chemical species.
They could be biological species
whatever. Here's a classic example of of
such an ansat. This is the uh the lotka
volta equations for predator and prey
which I'm sure many of you are very
familiar with. They were co-invented or
or invented independently by Alfred
Lotka and Vto Volatera near the
beginning of the 20th century. This is
what the classic lota equations look
like. There are two species. There is a
prey species and a predator species. And
those four terms are uh reproduction,
getting eaten, uh eating to reproduce
and background death rate. So uh if you
got those four terms, you get these nice
oscillatory solutions uh you know
between your predators and your prey
that arise. Okay. So this is a slightly
more general form of those lotka volta
equations. There is a linear part which
we'll call rx and uh in lotka volta that
linear part is diagonal. Uh so you know
the the uh the wolf can't turn into a
rabbit, the rabbit can't turn into a
wolf. So so the reproduction is
diagonal. And then there's also a
bilinear term which is the the part
where predation, competition and the
fact that niches are finite uh gets
implemented. So the the the right part
is suppressive. The left part makes
things grow. The right part makes things
uh um squish squish down. Keeps them
finite.
But this can't be the whole story of
evolution. Why can't it be the whole
story of evolution? Well, of course,
because it's closed-ended. Uh you know,
we only have two species here. It
doesn't matter how long you run this
damn thing. You're not going to get a
third species. Uh and uh and you're not
going to change the design space either.
uh you can have you know very
complicated terms in here that allow
finch beaks to adapt to different uh
environments but you have to have the
space of finch beaks predefined before
before this uh equation can even be made
to work. So uh this doesn't you know
this doesn't answer the question of how
evolution gets started. It doesn't
answer the question of what happens uh
afterward other than optimization to uh
to niches.
So uh now we bring in another uh Eastern
European uh Dimmitri Sergeovich
Meshovski. So he's the one who first
came up with the idea that maybe uh
mitochondria engaged in some kind of
simogenetic event in order to end up
inside other single-c cellled organisms
to make um to make ukarots. This was
popularized and proven to actually be
the case by Lin Margulus uh in in 1968.
Uh one of the really great papers in
biology from the 20 from the 20th
century. uh I'm sure many of you are
familiar with this is that paper sorry
1966 on the origin of mitosing cells. So
she's the one who proved uh that
ukarotes were actually a fusion between
two different kinds of procarots and
popularized this term that Medishovski
had invented symbioenesis.
Okay. So could symbioenesis be happening
as a as a source of novelty in BFF? Yes,
that is the source of novelty in BFF and
indeed that is the source of novelty in
evolution period. This is something that
Lin Margulus believed. Um but uh that
was not uh that had not been widely
accepted by the by the by the bi biology
community even by the time of her death
uh in 2011. Um you know so she she had a
much more expansive idea about about why
symbioenesis was important. Uh only the
particulars of chloroplasts and
mitochondria had been accepted. So the
way we can look for symbioenesis and BFF
is to look for replicators emerging
before that phase transition. And if you
look for them, if you just look for
stretches of bytes that are getting
copied during those interactions, you
find such stretches of bytes. They begin
short and kind of crappy, unreliable,
but they're there from the beginning.
Every time you have a single copy
instruction, after all, one bite is
getting copied from somewhere to
somewhere. So almost by definition, you
have at least one bite long sequences
that are getting copied right from the
beginning. So let's just call them
replicators, right? There are
replicators there from the beginning.
Now if you have these one bite
replicators that are copying themselves
back and forth now and then once in a
while they will come into conjunction
and two of them will will copy better as
a group than the than the two of them
copied on their own and that when that
happens then they'll start to copy as a
group and that is a symbiogenetic event.
uh and and so basically the reason that
even without uh mutation you get these
complex programs arising is because of
these fusion events between smaller
replicators.
So uh can one build singenesis into an
equation like uh like this one that you
know for for lot of volta you can this
is our statistical physicist who came up
with the right kind of term to write
mathematically for describing how
symbioenesis works. He wrote down an
equation for the coagulation of
polymers. Uh so this is uh small hovski
coagulation. Uh this is what happens
when clouds form. It's what happens when
gelatin sets in the fridge. Uh so the
idea is that you have uh let's say
polymers that begin uh as monomers you
know one monomer another monomer they
they stick together and now you have a
dimer and now the dimer and maybe
another monomer stick together and you
have a trimer. Uh two trimers stick
together and now you have a heximer and
so on. These are the equations for that.
This is the mass balance equation. It's
it's very simple. There's a merger gain
term and a merger loss term. The merger
gain term which scales like the
densities of the two things that are
coming together. Uh and the product of
those with some merger kernel K is
increasing the population of cluster K
which is of length I plus J. And then
you have to do the balance of that.
Every time you have two things coming
together to make a new one, you have to
then subtract their populations I and J.
And that's what the right hand side is
about. It's the loss of things that have
merged. So you put those two things
together and you get a stochastic
differential equation for mergers in a
solution.
And by the way there is a phase
transition associated with small husky
coagulation. It's called gilation. And
it's exactly what happens when you put
jello in the fridge and it sets.
Basically, if things are sticking
together and if they stick together with
a scaling exponent that is greater than
one, then you get this finite time
singularity in which the the the things
that stick together diverge to infinite
size and the whole thing sets no matter
how big it is. Uh and that's that's how
jello sets. Could that be galation? Yes.
Uh the short answer is that is gilation.
that phase transition uh that we see of
the emergence of life is ailation phase
transition according to a generalization
of smallhovki coagulation to this case
of BFF strings coming together if you if
you think about quote unquote inanimate
and viral replicators as being
replicators that uh that are not
self-contained in other words where the
code that runs is not fully within the
code that is actually getting copied
then you you you notice something
interesting so what I'm calling here an
inanimate replicator uh and very much in
scare quotes is uh is code that copies
something fully outside itself. In other
words, the code that runs in order to do
the copying is disjoint from the thing
that gets copied. Uh are there such
replicators in the real world? Of
course, that's what water is, right?
Water is a replicator of some kind. It
gets made by stuff, but the stuff that
it gets uh that it gets made from, you
know, like water is not a part of the of
the running process. I mean it is a part
of the running process that makes more
water in some cases but right it's it's
it's um it's it's not uh it's not part
of the code let's say viral is the case
in which the the code and the thing that
is copied overlap. So in other words
some of the code that does the copying
is actually some of the stuff that gets
copied but the uh the code is not fully
contained by what gets copied. So this
is a an an incomplete replicator that
would need to cooperate with another
replicator in order to reproduce. So
that's what I mean by viral. In the
beginning of BFF, all of the replicators
are inanimate and viral. The great
majority are inanimate and a few of them
are viral. A few of them happen to copy
uh you know one of those uh bites that
is actually an instruction that is doing
the copying. But as you move toward uh
the time of gilation which I've
normalized to one here, you can see that
cellular replicators suddenly emerge. So
they can't emerge before you know about
halfway through the run and they and
they shoot upward at the end. And that's
really interesting because that tells
you that that the moment of a cellular
replicator where the machinery for
copying yourself is part of the thing
that is copied emerges through the
symbiosis or the symbioenesis of
inanimate and viral uh replicators.
Okay. So a full equation would have two
terms. It would have this reproduction
and you know like a voltera type type
term and it would have a merger or
smallhovsky type term. One on the left
is normal population dynamics. That's
normal Darwinism. And the one on the
right, uh, you could think about the
left as evolution and the right as
revolution. Right? Those that's the
moments when things come together. Now,
the population dynamics part for BFF
looks like this. It's a little bit more
complicated, but it has the same basic
form as LKA volta. There's a linear part
on the left. I'm just writing that as a
matrix uh, RI operating on the on the
whole thing. And on the right u the
reason that looks a little bit a little
bit different from Lka Voltera is that
when something gets copied it overwrites
other stuff. So uh so now we have to say
well how does how does that suppress the
populations of everything else in the
soup? In order to figure that out you
have to look at niches what are the
bites where something gets copied and
the overlap between the niches of two
replicators tells you you know how much
one thing getting copied you know how
likely it is that that will overwrite uh
something else that shares its niche.
Uh, okay. The symbioenesis part is a bit
of a mess, so I'm not going to go
through it. Uh, I hope that's okay. But
it looks just like Small Hovsky, just
gnarlier. Um, the the reason that it's
gnarlier is because Small Hovsky has
only binary fusion uh between two parts.
And in BFF, sometimes a bunch of things
come together. So, you have to take into
account these kernels that have more
than two uh parameters in them. Also,
when things come together, they don't
necessarily look like the sum of of the
things that came together. You could
have something that is three bytes long
or something five bytes long come
together and the result that copies
itself is only two bytes, one bite from
each one or or anything uh right along
those lines. So to to account for those
complexities, you end up with a much
more complicated k term, but it's
essentially the same as as a small
huskulation. to prove that this kind of
symbioenesis is needed in order to get
uh these complex programs. Uh you you
can do a very simple intervention which
is uh when you're interacting two tapes
you can sort of do it in a sandbox
before committing and in the sandbox you
see whether uh whether a new replicator
arises and if so what replicators is it
made out of. In other words, uh you
know, when you look at the source, you
can see what you know whether whether
any of those uh source bytes were
actually the output the outputs of
copies of some previous replicator. And
if so, then you have a tree. You have an
ancestry tree for uh for that for that
replicator. That means that you can
think about the depth of such a tree. Uh
you know, how many things have come
together and you can limit the depth of
that tree. You can say if the tree depth
exceeds 10 for a new replicator, then
I'm going to I'm going to actually not
not do this [clears throat] interaction.
and I'm going to take them back apart,
pretend it never happened, put it back
in the soup, and try again. If you if
you limit the depth of the tree to say
24, then the number of operations that
you have to block, the number of
interactions you have to block is
actually very small. You only have to
block one in a thousand operations. But
that one in a thousand operations is
really important. As it turns out, if
you block those, no galation will
happen. You need uh at least tree depths
of 20 or so in order to get these
complex uh programs. So this is a very
nice proof that symbioenesis is what
what is needed in order to get to these
complex tapes. When you do that
blocking, you end up with sort of
logistic curves for the populations of
all the replicators in that soup. They
they they go up and then they saturate
and stabilize. That's fun because it
lets you do a little bit of math. So as
you can see, you know, that not only do
things go up and saturate, but then they
they there's some random uh oscillations
and those oscillations can be
correlated. Sometimes you can see the
two of those populations go up and down
together. So that means that they
they're maybe collaborating with each
other and sometimes they go in opposite
directions. They're anti-correlated and
that means that they're competing with
each other because they're you know one
is overwriting the other for instance.
So that's what one would expect from
from off diagonal production and
competition from those those equations I
wrote earlier. And if you linearize the
dynamics around that steady state, then
you can sample the correlations in those
population fluctuations and you can
reconstruct the matrix R. I will skip
the details of how one does this, but
this is a classic fluctuation analysis.
You solve the leaponov equation and you
get a Jacobian and from that you get the
matrix R. And the matrices R look really
cool. First of all, they have a strong
diagonal that tells you that by and
large things replicate themselves. uh
just as you would expect from Lka
Voltera. But uh there's some other stuff
going on here as well. Aside from that
dominant diagonal of self-replication,
there is some negative stuff off the
diagonal and some positive stuff off the
diagonal. The negative stuff off the
diagonal, you can see looks largely
symmetric about the diagonal. And that's
as you would expect too. Basically, if A
competes with B, then B competes with A.
Two things that are that are fighting
for the same niche are are in a kind of
zero sum relationship with each other.
But the cooperation part where where uh
where something helps something else is
not symmetric and that's as you would
expect too. Just because A helps B or
enables B doesn't mean that B enables A
or at least not directly. Right? So
they're complex cycles in this in this
graph on the right of of of codependency
or enablement.
So uh negative component is symmetric,
positive component is is asymmetric and
there's this big diagonal. Do the
submatrices that are about to undergo
symbioenesis have any special
properties? They do. So in other words,
if it's these let's say four rows and
columns that are about to about to
undergo symbioenesis, you can ask what
are the what are the igen values of that
matrix of that submatrix and it turns
out that that they are generally
cooperative. So essentially if you if
you were to pick random rows and columns
from this matrix then you get a
highdimensional picture of the rank of
the matrix. But when you look at the
ones that actually combine, it's much
lower rank. They're already uh working
together. So in other words, there's a
relationship between the R and K parts
of this equation. Symbioenesis happens
among guys who are already working
together. Not all the same, not
independent, cooperative. Here's another
really interesting thing. If you look
not at the R matrix but at the Jacobian
itself then you can find the signs of
imminent instability in it of when it's
about to pop when it's about to go run
away and gellate uh or gel you don't say
gelate you say gel right so in
particular if you block the depth of the
possible trees to a low number then uh
the igen vector the igen values of the
jacobian are always negative meaning
that the system is stable but as you
look at larger depth ceilings you find
that more and more of this leading igon
vectors or the real parts of those
leading igon vectors pop positive and
that means that the system is about to
blow. Uh you can keep it from blowing
for a while by keeping that merger clamp
on but it tells you that essentially the
more you evolve these things the more
they begin to cooperate with each other
and the more incipient symbioenesis is
about to happen. Uh and that's what
leads to this phase transition. Uh, all
right. Um, I I just want to put a little
plug in for what I think could be a
really beautiful missing link between
the kind of algorithmic information
theory that Ector Zanil was talking
about and the assembly theory that he
has somewhat slammed with a couple of
papers that he has written. But uh, you
know, as as those of you who have
followed that might know or might might
realize from what I've just talked
about, there's a very close relationship
between what I've just been describing
and assembly theory. It's things coming
together to make bigger things. But the
assembly theory proponents have have not
really talked about the computational
nature of what they're doing. And in
this I fully agree with with where
ectctor is coming from. Uh and the way
that those connect I think is by
starting to look at things like
conditional cologoral complexity of the
things that are coming together. So I
think this is a construction point for
us to maybe reconcile those two
different pictures. All right. So
symbioenesis is what gives you
complexification that in turn is what
gives evolution its arrow of time. uh in
classical evolution and Darwinian
evolution there's no reason that things
should become more complex over time uh
you know they might simplify they might
get more complex it doesn't matter but
uh with symbioenesis we know that things
get more complex because if A can
replicate itself and and survive into
the future and B can replicate itself
and survive into the future when they
come together you suddenly need A to
replicate itself and B to replicate
itself and there's some additional
information that has been added which is
how the two fit together uh and and
those those extra bits of information
that keep getting added to the program
of what is the large replicator, they
don't come from mutation. They come from
the fact that things encounter each
other randomly in order to possibly
undergo that symbiogenetic event. So
it's actually the thermal randomness of
the fact that we pluck two of these guys
out of the soup at random. That's the
the information source if you like or
the noise source that is selectively
turned into algorithmic information by
the symbioenetic process. yours and John
Mayard Smith have have uh have written
you know extensively about these major
evolutionary transitions in which
symbioenesis results in large novel
forms of life like ukarotes
multisellularity and so on uh and uh I
think this work is great but uh but the
flaw is that they're only talking about
eight events or 12 events and if if what
I'm saying is true then this is just the
tip of a gigantic iceberg basically it's
symbioenesis all the way down most of
these symbioenic events are much more
uneven. There may be just a little bit
of something getting incorporated into
something much bigger, but that is the
source of novelty in all of evolution.
These are just the most dramatic cases
that involve, you know, uh really really
big uh visible stuff happening. So, is
there evidence for these smaller
singogenetic events in biology? Lots
there's lots of evidence for it. So uh
you know I I don't have time to go into
it in any detail but if you look at at
just the human genome you find that you
know only 1 and a.5% of it codes for our
proteins and lots of the rest of it is
transposons and uh other endogenous uh
retroviral elements of various kinds
that involve viruses whose whose ecology
is our own genomes and that reproduce
inside our genomes and sometimes jump
species resulting in weird [ __ ] like uh
a quarter of the cow genome being a a
retroron that also lives and lizards and
salamanders and stuff. Uh, and so, you
know, when you start to look at that,
you you realize that that genomes are
fractal and it's replicators made of
replicators made of replicators just as
I've as I've described, not these kind
of uh, you know, fixed design space and
evolution only happening in its usual
way. It's not just horizontal gene
transfer in bacteria. This synogenetic
picture, I think, is is the engine uh,
that produces novelty throughout all of
life, including including big complex
animals like ours, like us. Um there's
more and more evidence in the in the
last decade of of things like this going
on. You know, for instance, the arc
virus uh was endogenized uh in in the
mammal lineage and you can find it in
our brains and it turns out that if you
knock out the ark virus in mice, they
stop being able to form new memories. So
clearly the arc virus is doing something
important for us and and that's a source
of novelty that that was an endogenized
virus. uh similar the mamalian placenta
uh was uh is formed by an indogenized
virus that fuses cell membranes together
and so on. Okay. So there's a definition
of life that comes out of this life uh
and I I said this uh you know in the
panel yesterday is an embodied
autopoetic computation arising and
complexifying through symbioenesis. It's
not just neuroscience that's
computational. Life was computational
from the beginning and it gets more
computationally complex over time
through symbioenesis at many scales
because remember if life is a computer
from the start then every time things
fuse together you're making a more and
more parallel computer. Those computers
have to be not only running the code
that model themselves and reproduce
themselves but that also do something
about modeling the other and figuring
out how they interact or work with the
other. And this means that an ecology of
functions is building up through
massively parallel computation that
becomes if you like more and more
intelligent with every one of these of
these fusions. And since symbioenesis
makes the computation massively parallel
uh that implies that intelligence and
life are very very closely connected. uh
which is why uh you know I ended up with
the book what is life as part of the
book what is intelligence when you're
not only using that intelligence to
model yourself but also to model your
environment which by the way includes
others most importantly then that's
intelligence and that means that life
was intelligent from the start and the
moment that that modeling of others
begins what we call in in larger more
complex animals theory of mind becomes
fundamental to the way intelligence
develops So uh you know these are really
simple simulations that show how uh you
know just persistence allows you know
the modeling of of of an environment to
turn into learning chemotaxis in these
fake bacteria. Uh but of course you know
in real life uh you're not only learning
about an environment that that exists in
isolation like the like the sugar
crystal but actually all of your friends
right the moment you're reproducing the
greater part of your environment is is
actually all of your all of the other
things that that uh you know even your
own reproduction is creating.
Uh life is never single player. Things
like intelligence explosions in in our
lineage in the hominins and in citations
uh and in bats and a variety of other
species are exactly this kind of runaway
modeling of others resulting in uh
growth of brains and growth of of groups
and and therefore that you know that
when we think about the growth of
advanced intelligence you know in in in
you know human societies or human brains
it's it's really that same sort of of
synogenetic process happening at a much
at a much higher level. Let's end there
and and switch to uh questions.
>> I think there are multiple different
ways to represent the symbiosis. I think
in the real biology we maintain those
high record structures and that there
are fundamental mathematical differences
how how you treat those symbiosis that
do you have any insight how we can
implement that? Yes, in biology we often
uh sort of raify one particular level of
detail and we say you know these are the
life forms and you know maybe there's a
symbiosis between uh you know let's say
you know algae and a sea slug but we
still think of the algae and the sea
slug as as as separate and we think
about population dynamics within that
rather than modeling them separately. Is
there a reason to prefer one scale or
another? You know, for me, one of the
lessons I the reason that I spent so
much time on the relationship between R
and K is that you can always move
something from one from from R to K and
back. Uh, you know, Lin Margulus
famously said we're just colonies of
bacteria, you know, some of which live
inside each other. And that's true. You
know, you could describe us as just
colonies of bacteria. But the reason
that it's useful to to move up a level
of detail is because you know humans
also you know reproduce as a unit you
know hence the mess and uh and there are
a lot of things that you can uh you can
learn about when you study at that
higher level uh a lot of abstractions
you can make from a computational
perspective that are hard if you're only
modeling at the lower level. So I don't
think that there's any there's any one
layer layer level that is true and we
have lots of boundary cases like lyken
or like uh colony insects right where
you can model the entire colony or you
can model the individuals I don't think
there's a right answer to those two uh
so you know do you do you keep a block
of rows and columns in R that are that
are uh that are in you know that always
end up or mostly end up getting copied
together uh or do you add a new row you
know it's it's it's actually a coarse
graining choice and you can make either
one
>> symbiosis is not symbiogenesis like you
What is the thing that you would claim
is kind of like you know a good insight
for how like you know A and B stop being
A and B in symbiosis and they become
something else. the fact that that uh
phase transitions don't come from R
alone, you know, but but you have to
look at K. Now, you you do you do get
this these runaway modes, right, which
which tell you that something is about
to is about to happen. But in order to
understand that phase transition, right,
in other words, in order to see that a
major evolutionary transition has
occurred, right, to put it in biological
terms, you you actually have to
understand the physics of K. It's only
by understanding the physics of K that
you can do the theory that lets you you
know predict and understand what is
going on right here. So you know if you
model a body as just a bunch of bacteria
then it's not wrong but but then uh you
know it's invisible to you that uh you
know that something amazing happened
when we became multisellular or when
ukarotes formed out of out of out of
bacteria. So this allows higher order
modeling and and in particular by the
way that higher order modeling you know
if we just take the subjective
perspective for a moment if you are one
of those bodies if you are one of those
people then you know you're not going to
survive very well if you're only
modeling other people as collections of
bacteria right you have to build higher
order models of them because that
becomes an essential part of your envelt
and you have to simplify or coar grain
the world in order to build a model that
is that is ecologically relevant to you
so uh you know I'm kind mixing here of
of subjective and and an objective
perspective. But the subjective
perspective ultimately is super
important. Uh you know it's a little bit
similar to like why do we need
temperature and pressure in physics? You
know those don't exist if we just look
at the microscopics. But it's only by by
coarse graining and looking at the
larger scale that you can understand
thermodynamics. And in the same way,
it's only by zooming out and looking at
the symbioenesis that you can understand
the dynamics of transitions of phase
transitions, messes and smaller and
coarser grained models that you know
where higher orders of things emerge.
>> Well, actually that's exactly what I was
doing like 30 years ago, right?
>> Exactly. That's that's why I began with
your nearly 30 years ago paper. There
was a big problem like it's always you
know the symbol is possible like you
know we burn the wood then it becomes
complicated coupling with each other
however the function itself is not
becoming complex or become high water
the function itself is just
>> I have three answers I suppose uh
depending on depending on which way we
we talk about it so uh first answer
actually comes from from software
engineering uh so composition or or from
mathematics for for that matter
composition of functions is uh
symbioenesis as as I've described it and
when you compose you know two functions
to make a a higher order function you
are making something more complex uh
than than the than the primitives uh you
know and and and you know the what I
hinted at with uh you know the Eric Eric
Mosnino's you know beginnings of
conditional complexity can quantify that
sort of compositional complexity you
could find signatures of it in you know
if you don't want to look in DNA you
could look in GitHub at the way you
every time somebody writes some code,
right? It it begins by importing a bunch
of other things and combining them and
and and and you you you do see a
tendency toward toward complexity. Now
that is constrained by energy. Uh you
know, the more complex a thing you make,
the the the more uh free energy it has
to use. But uh now you get uh some of
Chris Kempus's beautiful work in which
you see that there are energetic
benefits to teamwork. Uh right. So, so
the the the way the scaling laws work
for this uh which are also
environmentally dependent. I mean, you
know, I don't know Chris if you got to
like the snow the snowball earth type
stuff, but there were certain very
specific conditions at certain points in
the earth's history that became
favorable for ukarioenesis if I'm
remembering correctly and and and so
there there are some external conditions
as well. But the other cool thing is
that when you start to have more uh
complexity in the in the computers when
you start to have massively parallel
computation that greater intelligence
also unlocks new energy sources and and
that gives you a bigger budget to play
with uh which which in turn allows the
next me to take place. So I think
there's an energetic perspective,
there's a compositional perspective, a
comorical perspective, there's a scaling
law perspective that that can all come
to rescue uh that that uh that question,
but we should talk more about it. I'd
love to I'd love to get into this in
more detail.
>> It's essential for life to have some
functionality pointing for the brain
programs their strings in which their
functionality by external goals aka the
CPU.
>> I agree. So I made claims that maybe
sound contradictory. You know, one of
which was that, you know, Vonoyman is
embodied computation and different from
touring in that sense, but on the other
hand that BFF uh, you know, looks like,
you know, very much like a touring
machine. And um, and yet I I also said
it was embodied because I I made one
tape. So you know, even the question of
whether something is embodied or not is
a little bit perspective dependent as
well because in a in a Vonoyman system,
for instance, there's of course the same
rule operating at every pixel. You know,
you can ask yourself the question, is a
computer the thing that I make, you
know, with lots of parts, right? You
know, of the kinds that designed, or is
it just the operation of a single pixel?
The usual answer is to say what happens
at a single pixel is just the physics of
that world. But what constitutes the
physics and what constitutes the
computation is actually a movable
boundary. So uh you know embodiment is
is is essential in a very minimal sense
that you need to be able to uh to
operate on the the thing that is going
to you need to be able to make coins
essentially right in and um uh and in
ordinary um uh brain [ __ ] you you can't
make a quin because the data tape is
separate from the from the program tape
but you bring them together you're now
in the same realm as as a as a cellular
automaton albeit with a different coarse
graining of what you consider to be the
physics and what you consider to be the
the the code. Now I mean in our world we
know that it's possible to build
computers or else we wouldn't be able to
build computers and we wouldn't be here
either. Um but you know what constitutes
the physics if you like the the physics
that makes up computers itself had to
evolve. You know we began as I guess
nothing but a quant you know quantum
field theory and then things came
together you know into particles uh you
know and the particles come together
into atoms the atoms come together into
molecules and so on. Those are
essentially what I would call the
inanimate replicators right in in the
system. And and there there's a there's
an important phase transition when those
suddenly are rich uh form a rich enough
set that not only do you have an autoc
catalytic system as mold fontana would
have said but also that that you can
form a touring complete instruction set
and and therefore you know open the door
to generality of of computing. I hope
that I hope that makes uh some sense.
>> All right. I think we're
>> And yeah, I'm afraid we have to wrap up.
So, let's thank once again. [applause]
[applause]
>> Thank you so much for this amazing this
amazing talk. Great questions, too.